An Analysis of the Constitutions of Former Soviet Union States

Home
About
Constitutions
Analysis
Conclusions

Background

The fall of the Soviet Union, a hegemonic cultural and political power in Europe and Asia, produced a veritable explosion of states that rose from its ashes. These fifteen states, Armenia, Azerbaijan, Belarus, Estonia, Georgia, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Latvia, Lithuania, Moldova, Russia, Tajikistan, Turkmenistan, Ukraine, and Uzbekistan preceded their socialists republics and are internationally considered the successors of their corresponding Union Republics and not the Soviet Union. The three Baltic states, Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, prioritized integrating into the international community, which clashed with the near-total disengagement with the Russian-dominated post-Soviet sphere, and eventually joined the European Union (EU) and the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO). The forms of governments of the new states ranges from dominant-party to parlimentan to unitary presidential systems. Economic recessions that followed the USSR’s dissolution marked a period of the fall of the Gosplan, the state planning agency responsible for economic planning, and the rapid embracement of market economic policies. This resulted in “shock therapy” policies in the early 1990s, where trade liberalization, price liberalization, and privatization triggered a drop in GDP and budget cuts towards social programs like education and healthcare. Therefore, some common trends found in the original constitutions drafted for each state was molded by this acceptance of a liberal economy, with instituions like the central bank and private property explicitly mentioned as independent to the state institions. Pairing this with social policies, privatization and liberalization formed the foundations of citizens’ liberties within each constitution. Our analysis, then, is an evaluation of the commitments and prioties within the first sections of the constitutions of these post-Soviet republics and, in turn, how those commitments have been upheld in the following decades.

Methods

For this project, our team chose to analyze just the preamble and first chapter of the constitutions. This was a tough decision for us to make. Our other options including marking up the entirety of all of the documents, or limiting it even more to just the preambles. The drawback of doing the entire document was the time limit. Some of the constitutions came out to be thousands of lines long, and because we were doing out descriptive markup by hand, this would have taken us a long time. However, we seriously considered doing the full texts because by only analyzing the preamble and first chapter, we cannot make full claims about what the constitutions as a whole include or leave out, because it may be in a later chapter. We opted to do only the preamble and the first chapter so that we could analyze which themes were most important to each country.

Our team, to ensure an efficacious work process and acessible reading process, worked to define the elements that comprised the analysis of these documents. These elements are not all-encompassing, but are instead designed to be applicable to the body of text so as to make data collection informative and robust, but also efficient.

Individual Rights

Refers to any explicit mentions the following individual rights. Does not include 'value' commitments.

Types of Individual Rights

Protest - Right to petition or demonstrate against the government.
Citizenship - Anything pertaining to citizenship, naturalizations, or the explicit privileges of citizens.
Assembly - The right to assembly.
Legal - Concerning any legal protections such as reference to self-incrimination or indigent defense systems.
Vote - Includes explicit reference to the right to vote.
Racial-equality - Anything referring to religious, ethnic, gender, racial, etc equality
Liberty - Refers to more abstract mentions of "rights and freedoms" or liberty.
Misc - Used to mark other relevant rights, such as healthcare.

Nationalism

Includes mentions of national pride, history, patriotism, or responsibility

Religion

Any mention of religion, it's freedoms, or its role with relation to the state.

Religion Type

Secular - Refers to to either secularism or a separation of church and state.
State-religion - Used to mark mentions of a religion or faith that endorsed or even enforced.
Neutral - Pertians to more abstract mentions of a god or faith.

Government

Marks references to government structure and design that could not have been generally quanitified otherwise.

Sovereignty

Reference to the right of the individual state's right to exist and its sovereign status.

Capital

Explicit designation of a capital city.

Currency

Explicit designation of a currency.

Consent

Pertains to any mention of the consent of the governed. Generally includes the idea that the government belongs to the people or that state authority lies with the people of the state.

Elections

Reference to electoral proceedings. Not suffrage, but rather what types elections will be held and how.

Separation

Mentions of separation of powers and different branches of government (executive, legislative, judicial).

Parties

Reference to political parties and their definition, permittance, or prohibition.

Party System

0 - Political Parties are not allowed. There are none.
1 - This is a one-party state.
2 - This is a two-party state.
Multi - A plurality of parties may exist in this state.

Property

Reference to rights of public or private ownership.

Property Type

Public - Government ownership of property.
Private - Private property, may be individual or corporate.
Other - Any kind of mixed ownership arrangement between state and private entities.

Language

Explicit mention of language.

Language Type

Native - Mention of a language specific to the region or culture of this state.
Russian - Mention of the Russian language, which was, for a time, the standardized language of the Soviet Union.

International

Any reference to international politics or association. The role the state intends to have internationally.

Symbols

Official symbols representing the state including flags, anthems, coats of arms, etc.

Peace

Reference to harmony or order.

Treason

Reference to attempts to usurp the powers that be in the state. Any attempt to illegitimately remove established government.

Levels

Mention of levels of government (national, state, local, etc), their powers, and how they interact with one another.

Levels Type

Unitary - The federal government is completely dominant over the states and only allows it specifically enumerated rights.
Federalist - The federal government and the state government have specific rights that they share. State is left rights which the federal government doesn't define for itself.
Neutral - General reference to the levels of government.

Economy

Explicit definition of a state economic system

Economy Type

Free - Not completely free market, but reference to a capitalist, neo-liberal economy similar to the United States.
State - Reference to Socialism, Communism, or any control of the economy by the state.
Mixed - In between these two. The state will have more control of the economy than in an average capitalist system, but also allows some relatively greater amount of market activity.

Bibliography

"Armenia 1995 (rev. 2015)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Armenia_2015.
"Azerbaijan 1995 (rev. 2016)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Azerbaijan_2016.
"Belarus 1994 (rev. 2004)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Belarus_2004.
"Constitution of the Kyrgyz Republic." University of Minnesota Human Rights Library. Accessed April 26, 2024. http://hrlibrary.umn.edu/research/kyrgyzrepublic-constitution.html.
"Estonia 1992 (rev. 2015)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Estonia_2015.
"Georgia 1995 (rev. 2018)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Georgia_2018.
"Interesting Facts About Ukraine." World Vision. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.worldvision.org.uk/about/blogs/facts-about-ukraine/.
"Kazakhstan 1995 (rev. 2017)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Kazakhstan_2017.
"Latvia 1922 (reinst. 1991, rev. 2016)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Latvia_2016.
"Lithuania 1992 (rev. 2019)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Lithuania_2019.
Meyer, Madeleine. “Language and Geopolitics: A Case Study of the Former Soviet Union.” Towson University Journal of International Affairs, December 14, 2021. https://wp.towson.edu/iajournal/2021/12/08/language-and-geopolitics-a-case-study-of-the-former-soviet-union/.
"Moldova (Republic of) 1994 (rev. 2016)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Moldova_2016.
"Russian Federation 1993 (rev. 2014)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Russia_2014.
Rutland, Peter. “Democracy and Nationalism in Armenia.” Europe-Asia Studies 46, no. 5 (January 1994): 839–61. https://doi.org/10.1080/09668139408412202.
Schiffman, Harold. “Language Policy in the Former Soviet Union.” Language policy in the former Soviet Union. Accessed April 22, 2024. https://ccat.sas.upenn.edu/~haroldfs/540/handouts/ussr/soviet2.html.
"Tajikistan 1994 (rev. 2016)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Tajikistan_2016.
"Turkmenistan 2008 (rev. 2016)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Turkmenistan_2016.
"Ukraine 1996 (rev. 2016)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Ukraine_2016.
"Uzbekistan 1992 (rev. 2011)." Constitute Project. Accessed April 26, 2024. https://www.constituteproject.org/constitution/Uzbekistan_2011.

An Analysis of the Constitutions of Former Soviet Union States

Home
About
Constitutions
Analysis
Conclusions

Nationalism

PREAMBLE

PREAMBLE The Armenian People, accepting as a basis the fundamental principles of Armenian statehood and pan-national aspirations enshrined in the Declaration on the Independence of Armenia, having fulfilled the sacred behest of its freedom-loving ancestors to restore the sovereign state, dedicated to the strengthening and prosperity of the fatherland, with the aim of ensuring the freedom, general well-being, and civic solidarity of the generations, and affirming its commitment to universal values, adopts the Constitution of the Republic of Armenia.

CHAPTER 1. THE FOUNDATIONS OF CONSTITUTIONAL ORDER

Article 1.

The Republic of Armenia is a sovereign, democratic, social, and rule-of-law state.

Article 2.

In the Republic of Armenia, the power belongs to the people. The people shall exercise its power through free elections, referenda, as well as through state and local self-government bodies and officials prescribed by the Constitution. Usurpation of the power by any organization or individual shall be a crime.

Article 3. The Human Being, His Dignity, Fundamental Rights, and Freedoms

The human being shall be the supreme value in the Republic of Armenia. The inalienable dignity of the human being shall be the integral basis of his rights and freedoms. The respect for and protection of the fundamental rights and freedoms of the human being and the citizen shall be the duties of the public power. The public power shall be bound by the fundamental rights and freedoms of the human being and the citizen as the directly applicable law.

Article 4. The Principle of Separation and Balance of the Powers

State power shall be exercised in accordance with the Constitution and the laws, based on the separation and balance of the legislative, executive, and judicial powers.

Article 5. The Hierarchy of Legal Norms

The Constitution shall have supreme legal force. Laws shall conform to the constitutional laws, and sub-legislative normative legal acts shall conform to the constitutional laws and laws. In case there are contradictions between the norms of international treaties ratified by the Republic of Armenia and the norms of laws, the norms of the international treaties shall be applied.

Article 6. The Principle of Legality

State and local self-government bodies and officials shall have the power to perform only such acts for which they are empowered by the Constitution or laws. Bodies prescribed by the Constitution, based on the Constitution and laws and with the purpose of ensuring their implementation, may be authorized by the law to adopt sub-legislative normative legal acts. Authorizing norms shall comply with the principle of legal certainty. Laws and sub-legislative normative legal acts shall come into force after being published in the manner stipulated by law.

Article 7. The Suffrage Principles

Elections of the National Assembly and community councils, as well as referenda shall be carried out on the basis of universal, equal, free, and direct suffrage, by secret vote.

Article 8. >Ideological Pluralism and the Multipartisan System

Ideological pluralism and the multipartisan system shall be guaranteed in the Republic of Armenia. Parties shall be formed and operate freely. Equal legal opportunities for activities of the parties shall be guaranteed by law. Parties shall promote the formulation and expression of the people’s political will. The structure and activities of parties may not contravene the democratic principles.

Article 9. Guaranteeing Local Self-Government

Local self-government is guaranteed in the Republic of Armenia as one of the essential foundations of democracy.

Article 10. Guaranteeing Property

All forms of property shall be recognized and equally protected in the Republic of Armenia. Subsoils and water resources shall be exclusive property of the State.

Article 11. The Economic Order

The basis of the economic order in the Republic of Armenia shall be the social market economy, which shall be based on private property, freedom of economic activity, free economic competition, and through the state policy aimed at general economic well-being and social justice.

Article 12. Preservation of the Environment and Sustainable Development

The state shall promote the preservation, improvement, and regeneration of the environment, and the reasonable utilization of natural resources, governed by the principle of sustainable development and taking into account the responsibility towards future generations. Everyone shall take care of the preservation of the environment.

Article 13. Foreign Policy

The foreign policy of the Republic of Armenia shall be conducted on the basis of international law with the aim of establishing good-neighborly and mutually-beneficial relations with all states.

Article 14.The Armed Forces and Defense

The armed forces of the Republic of Armenia shall ensure the defense, security, and territorial integrity of the Republic of Armenia, and the inviolability of its borders. The armed forces of the Republic of Armenia shall maintain neutrality in political matters and shall be under civilian control. Every citizen shall be obliged to participate in the defense of the Republic of Armenia in the manner stipulated by law.

Article 15. Promotion of Culture, Education, and Science, Protection of the Armenian language and Cultural Heritage

The state shall promote the development of culture, education, and science. The Armenian language and the cultural heritage shall be under the care and protection of the state.

Article 16.Protection of the Family

Family, being the natural and fundamental cell of society and the basis for the preservation and reproduction of the population, as well as motherhood and childhood shall be under special protection and aegis of the state.

Article 17.The State and Religious Organizations

The freedom of activity of religious organizations shall be guaranteed in the Republic of Armenia. Religious organizations shall be separate from the state.

Article 18. The Armenian Apostolic Holy Church

The Republic of Armenia shall recognize the exceptional mission of the Armenian Apostolic Holy Church, as the national church, in the spiritual life of the Armenian people, in the development of its national culture, and in the preservation of its national identity. The relationship between the Republic of Armenia and the Armenian Apostolic Holy Church may be regulated by a law.

Article 19.Ties with the Armenian Diaspora

The Republic of Armenia shall carry out a policy aimed at developing comprehensive ties and preserving Armenianness with the Armenian Diaspora, and shall facilitate repatriation. Based on international law, the Republic of Armenia shall contribute to protecting the Armenian language and Armenian historical and cultural values in other countries, and advancing Armenian educational and cultural life in such countries.

Article 20.The State Language of the Republic of Armenia

The Armenian language shall be the state language of the Republic of Armenia.

Article 21.The Symbols of the Republic of Armenia

The flag of the Republic of Armenia shall be tricolor - with equal horizontal stripes of red, blue, and orange. The coat of arms of the Republic of Armenia shall depict, in the center on a shield, Mount Ararat with Noah’s ark and the coats of arms of the four kingdoms of historical Armenia. The shield is held by an eagle and a lion, while a sword, a branch, a sheaf, a chain, and a ribbon are depicted below the shield. The detailed description of the flag and the coat of arms shall be stipulated by law. The anthem of the Republic of Armenia shall be stipulated by law.

Article 22.The Capital of the Republic of Armenia

The capital of the Republic of Armenia is Yerevan.

An Analysis of the Constitutions of Former Soviet Union States

Home
About
Constitutions
Analysis
Conclusions

Armenia
Azerbaijan
Belarus
Estonia
Georgia
Kazhakstan
Kyrgyzstan
Latvia
Lithuania
Moldova
Russia
Tajikistan
Turkmenistan
Ukraine
Uzbekistan

Check a box to highlight an element:

Nationalism
Liberty
Government
Citizenship
Vote
Protest
Assembly
Legal
Racial Equality
Misc Rights
Capital
Symbols
Russian Language
Native Language

PREAMBLE

PREAMBLE The Azerbaijan people, continuing the traditions of many centuries of their Statehood, guided by the principles which are reflected in the Constitutional Act on the State Independence of the Republic of Azerbaijan, wishing to provide welfare for all and everyone, and to establish justice, freedom, security, and being aware of their responsibility before past, present, and future generations, exercise their sovereign right by solemnly declaring the following goals: to protect the independence, sovereignty and the territorial integrity of the Republic of Azerbaijan; to guarantee the democratic system within the framework of the Constitution; to achieve the realization of a civil society; to establish a law-governed, secular state which assures the supremacy of the law as an expression of the will of the people; to assure to all a decent level of life in accordance with a just economic and social order; to live under conditions of friendship, peace and safety with other peoples, maintaining a commitment to general human values and to implement a mutually beneficial cooperation for these purposes. For the sake of the above stated high intentions, this Constitution shall be adopted through a nationwide referendum.

FIRST PART. GENERAL PROVISIONS Chapter I. The Power of the People

Article 1. Source of Power

The Azerbaijan people are the sole source of State power in the Republic of Azerbaijan. The Azerbaijan people include citizens of the Republic of Azerbaijan that live in the territory of the Republic of Azerbaijan or outside the country and that obey the Azerbaijan State and its Laws. This does not exclude norms defined by the international law.

Article 2. The Sovereignty of the People

The Azerbaijan people have the sovereign right to freely and independently decide their fate and to establish the form of its own governance. The Azerbaijan people implement their sovereign right by universal elections-referendum and by their representatives elected on the basis of universal, direct and equal elections by secret and individual ballot.

Article 3. Matters to be determined by Referendum

The Azerbaijan people can settle every matter connected with their rights and interests by referendum. The below-mentioned matters can only be determined by referendum: The adoption of the Constitution of the Republic of Azerbaijan and the introduction of changes to it. The change of State borders of the Republic of Azerbaijan. A referendum cannot be held concerning the following matters: Taxes and the state budget; Amnesty and pardon; The election, appointment or confirmation of officials, whose election, appointment or confirmation are within the competence of the legislative organs and (or) the executive power.

Article 4. The Right to Represent the People

No one except authoritative representatives elected by the people have the right to represent, speak for and address on behalf of the people.

Article 5. The Unity of the People

The Azerbaijan people are united. The unity of the Azerbaijan people constitutes the foundation of the Azerbaijan State. The Republic of Azerbaijan is wholly and indivisibly the Homeland for all the citizens of the Republic of Azerbaijan.

Article 6. Banning of Power Usurpation

No part of the Azerbaijan people, either an individual, or a social group or an organization has the right to usurp the authority of the Azerbaijan people to exercise the power. Power usurpation is the most serious crime directed against the people.

An Analysis of the Constitutions of Former Soviet Union States

Home
About
Constitutions
Analysis
Conclusions

Click on each arrow to see conclusions

Conclusions

Individual Rights

Observations

Regarding individual rights, a generalized observation from our first graph in our analysis page shows that rights were mostly concentrated in the realms of citizenship, racial equality, and liberty, with 40%, 53%, and 93% respective mentions in all of the constitutions. Regarding citizenship and racial equality, it is inferred that countries provide a legal and enshrined emphasis on the freedom of mobility after the fall of the Soviet Union, considering initiatives in the past like the Independent State Society (CIS) that stressed the significance of each country’s sovereignty separate from Russian interference(Papava, 2008). Specifically with the CIS, a coalition of former Soviet countries outside the Baltic countries formed in 1995, this led to the failure of countries to actually respond to foreign policies regarding citizenship(Papava, 2008); as a result, the individual right to citizenship and racial equality mentioned in current renditions of constitutions highlight that despite Post-soviet countries establishing their sovereignty, there is still an altruistic obligation to suit the deployment of economic and human capital across their borders and are expected to hold that collective exchange. This is further emphasized with the GUAM Organization for Democracy and Economic Development established in 1997 by Georgia, Ukraine and Azerbaijan that set a new trend of regional integration with other post-soviet countries(Sanchez,2022).

This might not always be the case!

Although liberties under our individual rights tag was higher than 50 %, the freedom house score graph directly compares each country’s mentions of individual freedoms (which are mostly characterized as general rights that fall underneath a citizen’s right to governmental protection) to determine if each country’s current sociopolitical environment supports that reasoning. Although the percentage of the right to protest is already low, amongst other rights implying the right to outwardly oppose against the government, this displays that post-former states have generally met the criteria required to be considered free. For instance, free and independent media’s status has been labelled to fall under “strict, Soviet-style controls” (Cepoi, 2021), with Russia and Belarus elucidating those restrictions. Although the Russian constitutions guarantee freedom of expression, it recieved a 1 out of 6 for media protection on Freedom House due to legislative restrictions on both mass media enterprises and online publications(Freedom House, 2023). This reveals that although an analysis of each category of individual rights can be explicitly mentioned in this first chapter, this must be compared to their real-world applications to determine if the current government actually reflects similar sentiments.

Further Research

The small percentages allocated to voting rights and gender equality was concluded to be something worth researching into beyond the scope of the first chapter, with how early or how often those rights are mentioned could possibly place those rights to a similar degree to that of individual rights attributed to liberty. Since both coincide with universal suffrage, it would also be interesting to view this in comparison to the Soviet Union, which granted women the right to vote in 1912 (Rukhlman), and compare that to how women’s suffrage or even the scope of gender rights are portrayed in each country’s constitution respectively.

Nationalism and Some Further Connections

With liberty rights mentioned overwhelming in all constitutions, it is likely that the words we tagged as this attribute were generalized, and served as a broader and more conclusive representation of ideals that pair with the nationalism graph also seen in the analysis. An astute observation of each would prove that the constitutions crafted individual liberties to arise from the sovereignty of the nation, rather than a distinct category. This result can be seen with countries like Armenia and Ukraine, having a high number of mentions in the nationalism graph while also having this enshrined with the most mentions of individual rights. On the World Press Freedom Index, this puts these countries on on the “partly free” tier compared to the “not free” category other countries like Russia and Kyrgyzstan are on (World Press Freedom Index). To counter this, comparing this to a country on a lower tier of freedom from the same index, Russia has a slightly lower number of nationalism mentions but higher mentions of freedom, yet according to a 2019 poll by independent newspaper the Moscow Times, over 59% of Russians felt that the Soviet government "took care of ordinary people” compared to Russia’s current state. (The Moscow Times, 2019)

Methods

Elements

Our team, to ensure an efficacious work process and acessible reading process, worked to define the elements that comprised the analysis of these documents. These elements are not all-encompassing, but are instead designed to be applicable to the body of text so as to make data collection informative and robust, but also efficient.

ind_rights

Any guarantee of individual rights.

ind_type

protest
citizenship
assembly
legal
vote
racial-equality
liberty
misc

nationalism

Any mention of national pride, history, patriotism, or responsibility

religion

Any mention of religion, it's freedoms, or its role with relation to the state.

r_type

secular
state-religion
neutral

gov

Miscellaneous reference to government role and design.

sovereignty

Reference to the right of the individual state's right to exist.

capital

Explicit designation of a capital city.

currency

Explicit designation of a currency.

consent

The consent of the governed. Anything that references that government or power lies with the people of the state.

elections

Reference to electoral proceedings. Not suffrage, but rather what elections will be held and how.

separation

Separation of powers, different branches of government (executive, legislative, judicial).

parties

Reference to political parties and their definition, permittance, or prohibition.

p_type

0
1
2
multi

property

Reference to rights of public or private ownership.

prop_type

public
private
other

language

Explicit mention of a specific language.

lang_type

native
russian

international

Any reference to international politics or association. The role the state intends to have internationally.

symbols

Official symbols representing the state including flags, anthems, coats of arms, etc.

peace

Reference to harmony or order.

treason

Reference to attempts to usurp the powers that be in the state. Any attempt to illegitimately remove established government.

levels

Mention of levels of government (national, state, local, etc), their powers, and how they interact with one another.

l_type

unitary
federalist
neutral

economic

Explicit definition of a state economic system

e_type

free
state
mixed

PREAMBLE

PREAMBLE With unwavering faith and a steadfast will to strengthen and develop the state, which embodies the inextinguishable right of the people of Estonia to national self-determination and which was proclaimed on 24 February 1918, which is founded on liberty, justice and the rule of law, which is created to protect the peace and defend the people against aggression from the outside, and which forms a pledge to present and future generations for their social progress and welfare, which must guarantee the preservation of the Estonian people, the Estonian language and the Estonian culture through the ages, the people of Estonia, on the basis of Article 1 of the Constitution which entered into force in 1938, and in the referendum held on 28 June 1992, have adopted the following Constitution.

CHAPTER I. GENERAL PROVISIONS

Article 1

Estonia is an independent and sovereign democratic republic wherein the supreme power of state is vested in the people. The independence and sovereignty of Estonia are timeless and inalienable.

Article 2

The land, territorial waters and airspace of the Estonian state are an inseparable and indivisible whole. Estonia is politically a unitary state wherein administrative division shall be provided by law.

Article 3

The state authority shall be exercised solely pursuant to the Constitution and laws which are in conformity therewith. Generally recognized principles and rules of international law are an inseparable part of the Estonian legal system. Laws shall be published in the prescribed manner. Only published laws have obligatory force.

Article 4

The activities of the Riigikogu (Parliament of Estonia), the President of the Republic, the Government of the Republic, and the courts shall be organized on the principle of separation and balance of powers.

Article 5

The natural wealth and resources of Estonia are national riches which shall be used economically.

Article 6

The official language of Estonia is Estonian .

Article 7

The national colors of Estonia are blue, black and white. The design of the national flag and the national coat of arms shall be provided by law.

PREAMBLE

PREAMBLE We, the people of Kazakhstan,united by common historic fate, creating state on the indigenous Kazakh land, considering ourselves peace-loving and civil society, dedicated to the ideals of freedom, equality and concord, wishing to take worthy place in the world community, realizing our high responsibility before the present and future generations, proceeding from our sovereign right, accept this Constitution.

SECTION I. GENERAL PROVISIONS

Article 1

The Republic of Kazakhstan proclaims itself democratic, secular, legal and social state whose highest values are an individual, his life, rights and freedoms. The fundamental principles of the activity of the Republic are public concord and political stability; economic development for the benefit of all the nation; Kazakhstan patriotism and resolution of the most important issues of the affairs of state by democratic methods including voting at an all-nation referendum or in the Parliament.

Article 2

The Republic of Kazakhstan is unitary state with presidential form of government. The sovereignty of the Republic extends to its entire territory. The state ensures the integrity, inviolability and inalienability of its territory. The administrative-territorial division of the Republic, the status of its capital shall determine by law. Capital of Kazakhstan is the city of Astana. A special legal regime in the financial sphere may be established within the city of Astana in accordance with the constitutional law. The names “Republic of Kazakhstan” and “Kazakhstan” have the same meaning.

Article 3

The people shall be the only source of state power. The people shall exercise power directly through an all-nation referendum and free elections as well as delegate the execution of their power to state institutions. Nobody shall have the right to appropriate power in the Republic of Kazakhstan. Appropriation of power shall be persecuted by law. The right to act on behalf of the people and the state shall belong to the President as well as to Parliament of the Republic within the limits of the constitutional powers. The government and other state bodies shall act on behalf of the state only within the limits of their delegated authorities. The state power in the Republic of Kazakhstan is unified and executed on the basis of the Constitution and laws in accordance with the principle of its division into the legislative, executive and judicial branches and system of checks and balances that governs their interaction.

Article 4

The provisions of the Constitution, the laws corresponding to it, other regulatory legal acts, international treaty and other commitments of the Republic as well as regulatory resolutions of Constitutional Council and the Supreme Court of the Republic shall be the functioning law in the Republic of Kazakhstan. The Constitution shall have the highest juridical force and direct effect on the entire territory of the Republic. International treaties ratified by the Republic shall have priority over its laws. The procedure and conditions of the application in the territory of the Republic of Kazakhstan of international treaties to which Kazakhstan is a party are determined by the legislation of the Republic. All laws, international treaties of which the Republic is party shall be published. Official publication of regulatory legal acts dealing with the rights, freedoms and responsibilities of citizens shall be necessary condition for their application.

Article 5

The Republic of Kazakhstan shall recognize ideological and political diversity. The formation of political party organizations in state bodies shall not be permitted. Public associations shall be equal before the law. Illegal interference of the state in the affairs of public associations and of public associations in the affairs of the state, imposing the functions of state institutions on public associations shall not be permitted. Formation and functioning of public associations pursuing the goals or actions directed toward violent change of the constitutional system, violation of the integrity of the Republic, undermining the security of the state, inciting social, racial, national, religious, class and tribal enmity, as well as formation of unauthorized paramilitary units shall be prohibited. Activities of political parties and trade unions of other states, religious parties as well as financing political parties and trade unions by foreign legal entities and citizens, foreign states and international organizations shall not be permitted in the Republic. Activities of foreign religious associations on the territory of the Republic as well as appointment of heads of religious associations in the Republic by foreign religious centers shall be carried out in coordination with the respective state institutions of the Republic.

>Article 6

The Republic of Kazakhstan shall recognize and by the same token protect state and private property. Property shall impose obligations, and its use must simultaneously benefit the society. Subjects and objects of ownership, the scope and limits of the rights of proprietors, and guarantees of their protection shall be determined by law. The land and underground resources, waters, flora and fauna, other natural resources shall be owned by the state. The land may also be privately owned on terms, conditions and within the limits established by legislation.

Article 7

The state language of the Republic of Kazakhstan shall be the Kazak language . In state institutions and local self-administrative bodies the Russian language shall be officially used on equal grounds along with the Kazak language. The state shall promote conditions for the study and development of the languages of the people of Kazakhstan.

Article 8

The Republic of Kazakhstan shall respect principles and norms of international law, pursue the policy of cooperation and good-neighborly relations between states, their equality and non-interference in each other’s domestic affairs, peaceful settlement of international disputes and renounce the first use of the military force.

Article 9

The Republic of Kazakhstan shall have its state symbols - the flag, emblem and anthem. Their description and order of official use shall be established by the constitutional law.

An Analysis of the Constitutions of Former Soviet Union States

Home
About
Constitutions
Analysis
Conclusions

Armenia
Azerbaijan
Belarus
Estonia
Georgia
Kazhakstan
Kyrgyzstan
Latvia
Lithuania
Moldova
Russia
Tajikistan
Turkmenistan
Ukraine
Uzbekistan

Check a box to highlight an element:

Nationalism
Liberty
Government
Citizenship
Vote
Protest
Assembly
Legal
Racial Equality
Misc Rights
Capital
Symbols
Russian Language
Native Language

PREAMBLE

PREAMBLE WE, the plenipotentiary representatives of the people of the Republic of Moldova, members of the Parliament, STARTING from the age-old aspirations of our people to live in a sovereign country, expressed by the proclamation of independence of the Republic of Moldova, TAKING DUE ACCOUNT to the continuity of the Moldavian people statehood within the historical and ethnic framework of its growing as a nation, STRIVING to satisfy the interests of citizens of a different ethnic origin, which together with the Moldavians, constitute the Republic of Moldova people, CONSIDERING the rule of law, civic peace, democracy, human dignity, fundamental human rights and freedoms, the free development of human personality, justice and political pluralism as supreme values, BEING AWARE of our responsibility and obligations towards the previous, present and future generations, REASSERTING our devotion to overall human values and desire to live in peace and harmony with all world-wide peoples, in compliance with the unanimously acknowledged principles and norms of the international lawWe herewith adopt the Constitution of the Republic of Moldova, and declare it as the SUPREME LAW OF OUR SOCIETY AND STATE.

TITLE I. GENERAL PRINCIPLES

Article 1. State of the Republic of Moldova

The Republic of Moldova is a sovereign, independent, unitary and indivisible state. The form of government of the State is the republic. The Republic of Moldova is a democratic and governed by the rule of law State, in which human dignity, his/her rights and freedoms, the free development of human personality, justice and political pluralism represent supreme values and shall be guaranteed.

Article 2. Sovereignty and State power (

National sovereignty resides with the people of the Republic of Moldova, who shall directly and through its representative bodies exercise it in the manners provided for by the Constitution. Neither an individual person or a group of people, nor a social group, a political party or any other public organization may exercise the State power on their own behalf. The usurpation of the State power shall constitute the gravest crime against the people.

Article 3. Territory

The territory of the Republic of Moldova is inalienable. The borders of the country shall be sanctioned by an organic law under the observance of unanimously recognized principles and norms of the international law.

Article 4. Human rights and freedoms

Constitutional provisions on human rights and freedoms shall be interpreted and enforced in accordance with the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, other conventions and treaties to which the Republic of Moldova is a party. Wherever disagreements appear between the conventions and treaties on fundamental human rights to which the Republic of Moldova is a party and its domestic laws, priority shall be given to international regulations.

Article 5. Democracy and political pluralism

Democracy in the Republic of Moldova shall be exercised under the conditions of political pluralism, which is incompatible with the dictatorship or totalitarianism. No ideology may be instituted as official ideology of the State.

Article 6. Separation and cooperation of powers

In the Republic of Moldova the legislature, the executive and the judiciary shall be separate and cooperate in the exercise of the assigned prerogatives pursuant to the provisions of the Constitution.

Article 7. Constitution - the Supreme Law

The Constitution of the Republic of Moldova shall be the Supreme Law of the State. No law or any other legal act, which contravenes the provisions of the Constitution, shall have legal force.

Article 8. Observance of the international law and international treaties

The Republic of Moldova pledges to observe the Charter of the United Nations Organization and the treaties to which it is a party, to institute relationships with other states on the basis of unanimously recognized principles and norms of the international law. The coming into force of an international treaty containing provisions contrary to the Constitution shall be preceded by a revision of the latter.

Article 9. Fundamental principles regarding property

Property shall be public and private. It shall be constituted of material and intellectual goods. No property may be used to the prejudice of human rights, liberties and dignity. The market, free economic initiative and fair competition shall represent the main elements of the economy.

Article 10. Unity of the people and the right to national identity

The State foundation is laid on the unity of the Republic of Moldova people. The Republic of Moldova is the common and indivisible motherland of all its citizens. The State shall recognize and guarantee the right of all citizens to the preservation, development and expression of their ethnic, cultural, linguistic and religious identity.

Article 11. Republic of Moldova - a neutral State

The Republic of Moldova proclaims its permanent neutrality. The Republic of Moldova shall not allow the dispersal of foreign military troops on its territory.

Article 12. Symbols of the State

The Republic of Moldova has a flag, coat of arms and anthem. The State flag of the Republic of Moldova shall be a tricolour. The colours are arranged vertically in the following order from the flagpole: blue, yellow, and red. The coat of arms is printed on the central yellow stripe of the tricolour. The State coat of arms shall consist of a shield divided horizontally into two parts: the upper part being of a red chromatics and the lower part - blue chromatics with a superimposed auroch's head showing between its horns an eight-pointed star. On its right the auroch's head is flanked by a five-petalled rose, and on its left by a slightly rotated crescent. All heraldic elements present on the shield are of golden (yellow) colour. The shield is laid on the breast of a natural eagle holding in its beak a golden cross, in its right claw a green olive-tree branch and in its left claw a golden sceptre. The State anthem of the Republic of Moldova shall be established by organic law. The flag, coat of arms and anthem shall be considered the State symbols of the Republic of Moldova and shall be protected by law as such.

Article 13. State language, use of other languages

The State language in the Republic of Moldova is the Moldavian language, and its writing is based on the Latin alphabet. The State shall acknowledge and protect the right to the preservation, development and use of the Russian language and other languages spoken within the territory of the State. The State shall facilitate the study of languagesof widespread international usage. The manner of functioning of languages within the territory of the Republic of Moldova shall be established by organic law.

Article 14. Capital

The capital of the Republic of Moldova is the city of Chisinau.

PREAMBLE

PREAMBLE We, the multinational people of the Russian Federation, united by a common fate on our land, establishing human rights and freedoms, civil peace and accord, preserving the historically established State unity, proceeding from universally acknowledged principles of equality and self-determination of peoples, revering the memory of ancestors who have passed on to us their love for the Fatherland and faith in good and justice, reviving the sovereign statehood of Russia and asserting the firmness of its democratic basis, striving to ensure the well-being and prosperity of Russia, proceeding from the responsibility for our Fatherland before present and future generations, recognizing ourselves to be a part of the world community, do hereby adopt THE CONSTITUTION OF THE RUSSIAN FEDERATION.

SECTION ONE CHAPTER 1. THE BASIS OF THE CONSTITUTIONAL SYSTEM

Article 1

The Russian Federation - Russia is a democratic federative law-governed state with a republican form of government. The names Russian Federation and Russia are equivalent.

Article 2

Man, his rights and freedoms shall be the supreme value. The recognition, observance and protection of human and civil rights and freedoms shall be an obligation of the State.

Article 3

The bearer of sovereignty and the sole source of power in the Russian Federation shall be its multinational people. The people shall exercise its power directly, as well as through State government bodies and local self-government bodies. The supreme direct expression of the power of the people shall be referendum and free elections. Nobody may usurp power in the Russian Federation. The seizure of power or usurpation of State authority shall be prosecuted under federal law.

Article 4

The sovereignty of the Russian Federation shall extend to the entirety of its territory. The Constitution of the Russian Federation and federal laws shall have supremacy on the entire territory of the Russian Federation. The Russian Federation shall ensure the integrity and inviolability of its territory.

Article 5

The Russian Federation shall consist of republics, krays, oblasts, cities of federal significance, an autonomous oblast and autonomous okrugs, which shall have equal rights as constituent entities of the Russian Federation. A republic (state) shall have its own constitution and legislation. A kray, oblast, city of federal significance, autonomous oblast and autonomous okrug shall have its own charter and legislation. The federal structure of the Russian Federation shall be based on its State integrity, the unity of the system of State power, the division of matters of authority and powers between State government bodies of the Russian Federation and State government bodies of constituent entities of the Russian Federation, the equality and self-determination of peoples in the Russian Federation. All constituent entities of the Russian Federation shall be equal with one another in relations with federal State government bodies.

Article 6

Citizenship of the Russian Federation shall be acquired and terminated in accordance with federal law, and shall be one and equal, irrespective of the grounds on which it is acquired. Every citizen of the Russian Federation shall enjoy all rights and freedoms on its territory and shall bear equal responsibilities as envisaged in the Constitution of the Russian Federation. A citizen of the Russian Federation may not be deprived of his (her) citizenship or of the right to change it.

Article 7

The Russian Federation shall be a social state whose policy is aimed at creating conditions ensuring a worthy life and a free development of Man. In the Russian Federation the labour and health of people shall be protected, a guaranteed minimum wage shall be established, State support shall be provided for the family, maternity, fatherhood and childhood, to the disabled and to elderly citizens, the system of social services shall be developed and State pensions, allowances and other social security guarantees shall be established.

Article 8

In the Russian Federation the integrity of economic space, free flow of goods, services and financial resources, support of competition, and the freedom of economic activity shall be guaranteed. In the Russian Federation private, State, municipal and other forms of property shall be recognized and shall be protected on an equal basis.

Article 9

Land and other natural resources shall be utilized and protected in the Russian Federation as the basis of the life and activity of the peoples living on the territories concerned. Land and other natural resources may be subject to private, State, municipal and other forms of ownership.

Article 10

State power in the Russian Federation shall be exercised on the basis of its division into legislative, executive and judicial authority. Bodies of legislative, executive and judicial authority shall be independent.

Article 11

State power in the Russian Federation shall be exercised by the President of the Russian Federation, the Federal Assembly (the Council of Federation and the State Duma), the Government of the Russian Federation, and the courts of the Russian Federation. State power in constituent entities of the Russian Federation shall be exercised by bodies of State government formed by those constituent entities. The division of authorities and powers among State government bodies of the Russian Federation and State government bodies of constituent entities of the Russian Federation shall be established by this Constitution, the Federation Treaty and other treaties on the division of authorities and powers.

Article 12

Local self-government shall be recognized and guaranteed in the Russian Federation. Local self-government shall be independent within the limits of its competence. Bodies of local self-government shall not form part of the system of State government bodies.

Article 13

Ideological diversity shall be recognized in the Russian Federation. No ideology shall be proclaimed as State ideology or as obligatory. Political diversity and the multi-party system shall be recognized in the Russian Federation. Public associations shall be equal before the law. The establishment and activities of public associations whose goals and activities are aimed at the forcible changing of the basis of the constitutional order and at violating the integrity of the Russian Federation, at undermining its security, at creating armed units, and at instigating social, racial, national and religious strife shall be prohibited.

Article 14

The Russian Federation shall be a secular state. No religion may be established as the State religion or as obligatory. Religious associations shall be separate from the State and shall be equal before the law.

Article 15

The Constitution of the Russian Federation shall have supreme legal force, direct effect and shall be applicable on the entire territory of the Russian Federation. Laws and other legal acts, which are adopted in the Russian Federation, must not contradict the Constitution of the Russian Federation. State government bodies, local self-government bodies, officials, citizens and their associations shall be obliged to observe the Constitution of the Russian Federation and laws. Laws must be officially published. Unpublished laws shall not have force. Any normative legal acts concerning human and civil rights, freedoms and obligations shall not have force unless they have been officially published for the information of the general public. Universally recognized principles and norms of international law as well as international agreements of the Russian Federation should be an integral part of its legal system. If an international agreement of the Russian Federation establishes rules, which differ from those stipulated by law, then the rules of the international agreement shall be applied.

Article 16

The provisions of this Chapter of the Constitution shall constitute the fundamental principles of the constitutional order of the Russian Federation and may not be changed except in accordance with the procedure established by this Constitution. No other provisions of this Constitution may conflict with the fundamental principles of the constitutional order of the Russian Federation.